[Music]
平行折第二部分
对称和非对称平行折
materials we'll be using a glue scissors
需要用的材料 胶水 剪刀 卡纸
and cart and I've explained all about
在这系列前奏课程里解释过了
these in the introduction to this series
of tutorials so there are three basic
这里是平行折的三种基本形态
types of parallel folds this is the
第一个是平行四边形
parallelogram that we looked at in
在第一部分讲过了
parallel folds part one and when when
页面完全展开时
the page is flat the parallelogram goes
平行四边形也会摊平
flat the other two types they stay in
另外两种
dimension when the page is flat so first
页面展开时 它们也是立体的
kind this is the basic parallel fold
首先看下基本平行折
equal the lengths on each side of the
立起结构两侧
pop-up are both the same and the
长度都是相同的
distance out from the central gully of
中间谷沟到两边的距离
the base they're both the same so on the
也是相同的
Left you've got a short length in a long
也就是左侧的 短底边 + 侧面长度
one and on the right you've got a short
等于右侧的 短底边 + 侧面长度
length and a long one
we'll be dealing with that today and the
一会再来细讲
other one is the asymmetric parallel
另一个是非对称平行折
fold so here's the asymmetric parallel
是长这样的
fold all four lengths are different
四个边长度都是不同的
you've got a short length on on the base
基础页两个边
and a long one and a long length on the
一个长 一个短
pop-up and the short one on the left
立起结构也是一个长 一个短
you've got a short base long piece on
左边是短的基础页和长的立起结构
the pop-up on the right you've got a
long piece on the base and a short piece
右边是长的基础页和短的立起结构
on the pop-up and the base plus the plus
两侧各加起来是同样大小
the pop-up on each side paid balance so
因此达到均衡
as you close it the pop-up closes so
合上立体书时 能完美闭合
we're going to be dealing with these two
现在从第头详细说起
- 制作多样的对称平行折
now I say you have to make one of these
开始动手吧
basic parallel columns you take a base
先制作一个基本平行折
sheet fold it in half crease the base
拿出张卡纸做基础页
really thoroughly and then we take a
对折 折彻底
piece to build with let's have pink bit
再拿张卡纸做结构 还是骚粉色吧
okay I'm going to actually show you
我想要演示的是
three different variations of this so
三种不同的效果
we'll just cut off three pieces so
所以剪三块卡纸
there's no importance to the dimensions
尺寸不强做限制
of these they're just as you know
你可以按自己想法
whatever whatever you want for your
随意设计
design basically so this is the first
这是我们第一个要做的
time I'll make so take the piece of card
拿出卡纸
fold this in half it's symmetrical so
对折 它是对称的
it's folded in half creased really
折彻底
thoroughly and then with it folded in
先折起来
half fold gluing tabs onto the outer
给边上折出上胶水的粘口
edges fold these thoroughly open it up
翻开粘口
and fold fold the creases individually
逐一强化下折痕
and the same on the other end from there
另一边也一样
night I always just trim off the corners
通常我会修剪下粘口的边角
right and this it's depending on what
怎样粘取决于
you want in your design it can be it can
你是怎么设计的
be glued down really close to the spine
可以粘的离基础页脊柱很近
so you've got a tall thin shape or you
得到高又瘦的形状
can go flatter and flatter further and
或者是更扁平的
further you can even stick it out so
更极致点
it's flat then it'll still work I'll
可以是平摊在基础页 也是OK的
show you one of those in a book in a
待会会举个书本里应用的例子
minute so we'll just glue this on so
现在先完成手头这个
we've got the two lengths on the pop-up
可以看到立起结构
they're both the same so we need the two
两侧长度是相同的
lengths on the base to be the same as
所以我们需要基础页上两边距离也相等
well so put just put glue just on one
开始上胶水
end so use the glue on one end smear it
先给一侧上胶水
to the crease and glue it down I'm going
涂均匀
about two centimeters out actually I
因为想要高一点的效果
want it a bit higher up the page so I'm
大概离开中折线两指宽
gonna put two more on the same page so
一会这个基础页上还要粘
there's that soundly glued put the put
另外两个结构
the pop-up into it's close position put
粘好一侧后 把立起结构收到折合状态
glue on the other end
给另一边上胶水
smear it up close the base so it finds
涂均匀  合上卡纸
its natural sticking position there it
粘口会自动粘到相应位置
is the basic symmetric parallel fold the
这就是基础对称平行折
two loads on the pop-up are the same and
两侧边的长度相同
the two lengths on the base of the same
基础页到两边距离也相同
so here's the second variation so this
这个是平行折第二种形态
is it it's very similar to the first
和第一种大体是相似的
except it's got a flat plain on the top
除了顶部这块是平的
so I'll turn this around so you can see
我把刚第一种侧过来
see how it works better so again we take
就能看出区别
this the strip of card we fold it in the
开始制作这个
middle we fold it well though in this
拿出片卡纸 对折
case it's not quite as important we we
是否折彻底 在这个结构不太重要
fold a tab onto each end again we want
折出粘口
it all symmetrical so we fold the gluing
因为结构是对称的
tabs with the whole piece folded in half
可以在折合状态的卡纸
so here are the gluing tabs fold them
同时折两个粘口
fold them well fold them individually
粘口折痕逐个加强下
fold them backwards
背面也折下
but with though is I'll just trim off
照例修剪粘口的边角
the corners right and in this case to
这个结构
get the flat piece on the top you just
我们需要顶部是扁平的效果
put a bit of put a bit of glue into the
所以给立起结构
into the top of the top of the pop-up so
顶部内侧上点胶水
there's some glue though and close it
涂匀 合起来
down and this one because I'm making it
这个刚剪得比较小
with such a short piece you can't go
所以不太好展示拉宽点的效果
really wide so we're going to have it
就制作成
much closer closer to the spine the tabs
就靠近基础页脊柱吧
can either be sticking out like this or
粘口可以这样粘到外面
you can fold them away underneath I
也可以藏到结构地下
think actually in this case is quite
现在这个情况
interesting having them on the outside
粘外面更好点吧
so I'm going to glue them put the glue
上胶水吧
on the outside and glue one side first
给一边的外侧先上胶水
so in order to get the symmetry we'll
为了保证得到对称效果
glue one side first and glue it into
先给一侧上胶水
place so here we are
我来了
and then we close the close the pop-up
放到立起结构
piece down put glue on the other other
给另一个粘口上胶水
tab smear it to the edges and close the
涂均匀 合上基础页
base so it finds its natural sticking
粘口会自动对齐自然的位置
positions so there's the second
这就是第二种
variation the third one is even more
第三种更简单点
simple the third one fold it in half and
首先卡纸对折
this time there are no gluing terms this
这次不需要专门折粘口
time we're making a curved shape these
我们要做个弧形形状
are quite unusually pop-up so this time
在立起结构里相对少见些
we just put a little bit of glue on the
给立起结构外侧边缘上点胶水
outside edges of the the pop-up we can
do both at the same time but so just
可以同时给两边都上
smear the glue onto the onto the bottom
底部外侧胶水涂匀
of the outside edges of the popper
and then set it into there this is
放置到这个位置
actually slightly fat so I'm just going
发现有点宽了
to take a srimad piece off so I'm fit
需要修剪窄一点
within your page right put that into the
来适配页面
flush into the gully close the base open
放到基础页边上 合上基础页 再打开
it up and we're getting a curve shape so
这就是弧形形状了
these are three three variations on the
以上就是平行折的三种形态
symmetric parallel fold or give you
different different potential when
可供你设计立起结构时选择
you're doing your pop-up designs oh I'll
show you something of a book now so this
下面展示在立体书中的实例
is this is robots by yumping Caskey if
《机器人》
we look at the final spreads this this
来看下最后一个跨页
is their parallel folds this is an
这是个平行折
equilateral parallel for both their both
准确说是等边平行折
sides are the same it actually the
立起结构两侧边的长度相同
lengths on the pop-up are the same as on
跟基础页的边长度也是相同的
the on the base so when the base is flat
所以基础页完全展开时
the whole pop-up post flow so that
立起结构也会摊平
that's an equilateral parallel fold
这就是为什么说是等边平行折
there if we look to the other end of the
来看另一页
book and there's just a very small
这是个小例子
example here this the head I think she's
这应该是个机器人吧
a robot the head of the robot is
她的头就是平行折
parallel folds and her head scarf is so
头巾也是
these are the same type of paranoia
以上都是跟我们
folds as we made the first one right
制作的第一个平行折同理
here we turn it round we can see it more
我来转个方向看着更明显
clearly here's the head of the robot
来看机器人头这里的两个平行折
we've got two you've got the head is one
一个是头本身
parallel fold and the head scarf is
一个是头巾
another as as you close it you can see
合上页面时
it and then this one the lengths on the
能看到立起结构的长度
pop-up are bigger than the notes on the
是比基础页长度长的
base that's why it stands up in 3d and
这就是为什么能立体起来
there's a final one I've got here that
这是最后一例
roaring lion tales by ron van der Meer
《狮子吼》
and this this is a parallel fold it's a
这里是个平行折
massive parallel fold
比较巨大的平行折
it's got added added creases which are
侧面边加了折痕
what sculpt the shape so if you pull it
用来丰富造型
out pull out these folds you can see
如果我们把造型拉起来
that what we've got here
就可以看出
it's just one big big parallel fold as
它就是个大大的平行折
you as you close it the whole thing the
合闭页面时
whole thing goes flat and by adding
所有元素会摊平
these extra creases he's done a
因为添加这些额外折痕
beautiful sculptural effect on this
产生了优美的动态雕塑效果
pop-up so he's created a real 3d shape
立体效果棒棒哒
out of the parallel fold by adding
除了平行折
adding extra creases
还有些别的元素
he's also cut a hole in one side so he's
像这边在侧面开了个山洞
he's really gone to turn you can look inside
他想吸引你朝里面看
and and see inside the structure the
欣赏内部的一些结构
palm trees they're coming up through
棕榈树是用了插槽技巧
slots the slots are another another
在后面课程里会讲解
tutorial later in this series that's the
到这里
end of the symmetric parallel fault now
对称平行折部分就结束了
I'll show you the asymmetric parallel
下面来看非对称平行折
- 非对称平行折边长讲解
fold this is an example all four lengths
这是个非对称平行折例子
are different the shot to a short in a
四个边都是不同的
long length on the base and I shortened
基础页上有一个短边 一个长边
a long length on the on the pop-up and
立起结构也有一个短边和一个长边
it's important to have the lower length
比较重要的点
on the pop up above the short length on
立起结构比较长的边在短边基础页上方
the base and vice versa the short length
反之亦然
on the pop-up above the long length I
短的立起结构在长的基础页上方
can actually do a really quick diagram
来画个简图解释下其中数学原理
of how this how this works mathematic knees
knees basically you have the here's your
here's your book and you've got the
pop-up is something like this so you
could call it if this was one this
length was four this was three this was
two so from one side from here to here
well weigh as 1 plus 4 and the other way
3 plus 2 let me just show you it's got
to balance on each side so on the left
on the base you got 3 on the pop-up
you've got 2 on the other side and the
base you've got 1 on the pop up you've
got 4 so you've got 5 the sum is 5 on
each side the other thing to make it
stand up the pop-up has to be bigger
than the base so on the base you've got
3 plus 1 on the pop-up you've got
four plus two so the base length is
total total for the pop up length for
total is six so now we'll just make one
of those baseships bonded in power and
this film this one is similar to the
ones we just made there are actually two
variations so take a piece of card to
make them reads and this will do so just
I'll just cut a narrow strip off on one
side so we folder tab onto each end and
then fold them really thoroughly as
usual cut off the corners so you don't
snag against anything and then fold fold
1/3 D and the third parallel fold you
know somewhere well off center so there
it is so we've got a short length and a
long length now in this type you again
simulated a parallelogram
you actually line up the central fold of
the pop-up with the gully of the base
mark the mark the short sides you only
need a little mark here because you're
not going to be sticking to that mark
you just need to know how long the short
side is and now the crucial bit you flip
it over so you're going to be sticking
the long side somewhere somewhere in
that region so put some glue on that
long tab
and the important thing is don't stick
it don't stick it to the mark if you
stick it to the mark what you'll get is
a parallelogram so in this case you
stick it closer to the spine than the
mark so just I'll just stick it about
halfway and according to where you stick
it it will give you different shapes so
stick it about half way fold the whole
piece into its closed position
put glue on the other tab here we are
smear it right up to the crease and then
folder fold the base shut so this one is
actually gonna stick out how it's
slightly this is this is just classic
when you're doing a rough you'll
regularly get the bits that stick out so
there it is this is the asymmetric
parallel for both the asymmetric
parallel fold and the symmetric parallel
fold they're both really useful for
other mechanisms for more complicated
method mechanisms there the analyzed
structure for floating planes and you
can raise planes above the base using
these two and then building
parallelograms onto them and we will
deal with that in another tutorial
on floating planes so I'll just I was
just going to show you how to add
another asymmetric bendy shape so in
that case yeah you take the take your
card and in this case you actually fold
it in the middle so you make a crease
right in the middle followed that pretty
well and then you put you put glue on
one one end you putting it on the
outside you you just glued quite a short
amount of the card on the other end
again on the outside you glue a longer
piece of the card so you know just smear
it well over the the surface and then
you you put that put the end flash into
the gully glue it down
and then close the piece and and shut
the base and so what you get with this
is a an asymmetric curving shape these
aren't these these pop-ups with straight
edges these are rigid shapes that you
can build on easily this type is a it's
not a it's not a rigid shape it bounces
around so these aren't good for
structure they're good for decoration or
you can stick small pieces onto them
that all just up at interesting angles
but they're not they're not structures
for for extending like like the like the
rigid shapes so yeah you know you can
have pieces like this that are just out
you can have pieces like like this sort
of jutting out that come up at the
interesting angles so you can play
around with them like that but you
cannot build you cannot build rigid
structures under them so that's
asymmetric parallel form so I'll just
show you a couple of examples oh this is
yeah this is another another more
extreme example of that one we just made
and then this was one I made this is
some this is an asymmetric parallel form
so it's got a big window cut in it
there's another asymmetric parallel form
underneath it and then this is another
asymmetric parallel forms built into
this gully here so if you actually look
at it and on you you can see how this is
both the the inner brown one and the
bigger green one they're both built into
the gully created by the car so this is
this is the asymmetric parallel fold in
action and then I've got a very small
one I can show you in this book bow-wow
by Chuck Murphy and in this case it's
underneath the circle and you open it at
the top this is just this is a v-fold
the cyclist but the dog the structure
the dog is a
loading plain this is a dog floating
parallel with with the base sheet but if
you look at it end on you'll see that
there's an asymmetric parallel folds
used to raise a parallelogram and the
dog is stuck to the top of the
parallelogram so that's an example of
using asymmetric parallel files to raise
a floating plane so that's it for this
this tutorial and everything I've said
is explained in this book pop-up design
and paper mechanics it's explained in
greater detail
[Music]
[Applause]